<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title/><link>/</link><description>Recent content on</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Current Technical Focus Areas</title><link>/posts/current_technical_focus_areas/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/current_technical_focus_areas/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="dataframe-operations-a-framework-agnostic-library"&gt;DataFrame Operations: A Framework-Agnostic Library&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dataframe operations form the foundation of modern data science workflows, yet researchers often face vendor lock-in when choosing between different dataframe frameworks. My work addresses this by developing a unified operations library that abstracts away framework-specific implementations. The challenge lies in handling the fundamental differences between these systems—some pandas-like dataframes use row-by-row operations, others employ lazy evaluation with native expressions, some require distributed execution patterns, while others focus on parallelization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve implemented operations like merge, reduce, replace, forward-fill, and mathematical transformations that work identically across all frameworks. Extensive benchmarking infrastructure—with synthetic datasets at small, medium, and large scales—ensures performance optimization while maintaining consistent behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/dataframes.png" alt="DataFrames" style="max-width: 600px; width: 100%; height: auto;"&gt;</description></item><item><title>Scientific Topics of Interest</title><link>/posts/scientific_topics_of_interest/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/scientific_topics_of_interest/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="intrinsically-disordered-proteins-idps"&gt;Intrinsically Disordered Proteins (IDPs)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most knowledge about proteins concerns structured proteins with specific functions. However, most proteins don&amp;rsquo;t have a particular or unique structure, and this doesn&amp;rsquo;t imply a lack of function. This makes IDPs incredibly interesting. The formation of protein-protein interactions underlies how proteins evolve to perform different functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/idps.gif" alt="IDPs"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>/about/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/about/about/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="short-bio"&gt;Short bio&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, I am Yerko Escalona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My educational journey has been a significant part of my life. I started my academic path by studying biotechnology at the &lt;a href="https://ciencias.uchile.cl/" target="_blank"&gt;University of Chile&lt;/a&gt;, where I specialized in Structural and Computational Biology. Later, I earned a doctoral degree at the University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences Vienna (&lt;a href="https://boku.ac.at/en/" target="_blank"&gt;BOKU&lt;/a&gt;), focusing on Molecular Dynamics, Data Sciences, and Python Development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I work as a Data Engineer at &lt;a href="https://www.novasign.at/" target="_blank"&gt;Novasign&lt;/a&gt;, where I play a crucial role in bridging the consulting and development teams. Here, I get to apply my diverse set of skills to innovate and collaborate effectively on diverse biotechnological projects.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>/publications/publications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/publications/publications/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="som-research"&gt;SOM research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Escalona, Yerko&lt;/strong&gt;, Drazen Petrov, Edgar Galicia-Andrés, and Chris Oostenbrink.
2023. &amp;ldquo;&lt;span class="nocase"&gt;Exploring the Macroscopic Properties of Humic Substances
Using Modeling and Molecular Simulations&lt;/span&gt;.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Agronomy&lt;/em&gt; 13 (4): 1044.
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/agronomy13041044" target="_blank"&gt;https://doi.org/10.3390/agronomy13041044&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galicia-Andrés, Edgar, &lt;strong&gt;Escalona, Yerko&lt;/strong&gt;, Mathias Gotsmy, Chris Oostenbrink, and Drazen Petrov.
2023. &amp;ldquo;&lt;span class="nocase"&gt;Molecular Dynamics Simulations up to Earth: Modeling of Soil Organic Matter&lt;/span&gt;.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Reference Module in Chemistry, Molecular Sciences and Chemical Engineering; Comprehensive Computational Chemistry&lt;/em&gt;, Elsevier.
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-821978-2.00106-9" target="_blank"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-821978-2.00106-9&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Escalona, Yerko&lt;/strong&gt;, Drazen Petrov and Chris Oostenbrink.
2021. “&lt;span class="nocase"&gt;Modeling soil organic matter: Changes
in macroscopic properties due to microscopic changes&lt;/span&gt;.”
&lt;em&gt;Geochimica Et Cosmochimica Acta&lt;/em&gt; 307: 228–41.
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2021.05.035" target="_blank"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2021.05.035&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>